<article xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'>
<info>
<title>PerfectTIN Manual</title>
<author><personname>
<firstname>Pierre</firstname>
<surname>Abbat</surname>
</personname>
<personblurb>NC PLS</personblurb>
</author>
<pubdate>2019</pubdate>
</info>

<section id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>PerfectTIN is a program for converting a point cloud to a TIN.</para>
</section>

<section id="window">
  <title>Main Window</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="window1.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para>At the top of the window is the menu. Under it is the toolbar, with four buttons denoting measuring units. The currently selected unit is the US survey foot.</para>
  <para>The largest part of the window is the canvas. In the middle of the canvas is the TIN, with each triangle colored by slope. A blue-and-yellow ball runs around the canvas, indicating that PerfectTIN is working. The ball spins to indicate how fast it makes changes to the TIN. In one of the bottom corners is a scale bar.</para>
  <para>At the bottom of the window is the status bar. It indicates, from left to right:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>the files loaded or the file being made;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>the number of dots or triangles;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>the tolerance in meters (.025×8 means that PerfectTIN is currently using a tolerance of 200 mm while working toward a tolerance of 25 mm);</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>the percentage of area that is within tolerance;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>the percentage of time it's busy, averaged over all worker threads.</para>
    </listitem>
</section>

<section id="units">
  <title>Units</title>
  <para>PerfectTIN can read and write files in meters, international feet, US survey feet, and Indian survey feet. Internally, it holds all coordinates in meters.</para>
  <para>You can set the unit in two places: <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and the toolbar. Also, whenever a TIN is displayed on the screen, it shows a scale in meters or feet.</para>
</section>

<section id="maketin">
<title>Making a TIN</title>
<para>To make a TIN, do the following:</para>
<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Set the unit with the toolbar button.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Load the point cloud file with <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the point cloud is in more than one file, load the other files.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Set the vertical tolerance with <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Start the conversion with <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Convert</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</article>

<section id="resume">
  <title>Resuming an interrupted conversion</title>
  <para>If converting a point cloud to TIN has been interrupted, for example by a power failure, you can resume it. Let's say that you were converting <filename>foo.las</filename> to <filename>foo.ptin</filename> and the computer crashed in the middle of the process.</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Start PerfectTIN.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Do <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and look for two files with names like <filename>foo.16.ptin</filename> and <filename>foo.8.ptin</filename>. Open the one with the smaller number.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>If PerfectTIN says that the file was not completely written, open the one with the larger number. This means that the computer crashed while it was writing the file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Do <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Resume</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The conversion will resume and hopefully run to completion.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
